Finding Aid for Henry D. Jones Papers
Bentley Historical Library
Henry D. Jones Papers
1918-1987
Bentley Historical Library
Jones, Henry D. (Henry David), 1900-1987
89202 Aa 2
1 linear foot
Presbyterian clergyman, missionary to China and Japan. Diary, 1918, detailing study at Ripon College and service in the Students' Army Training Corps; files relating to foreign missionary activities, including photographs; correspondence, 1935-1986; articles and biographical material; and personal and professional miscellanea relating in part to his interest in the history of Welsh Americans in Michigan.
The collection was donated by Mrs. Henry D. Jones (Donor No. 4793 ) on October 20, 1988.
The collection is open for research.
Henry David Jones was born May 10, 1900 in Chicago, Illinois. In 1918, he enrolled in Ripon College under the auspices of the Student Army Training Corps. Following his graduation in 1923, he entered McCormick Theological Seminary. While studying in seminary he was director of boy's work at Howell House, a mission outreach to the foreign-born living on the southwest side of Chicago. He received his ordination in 1926, and was appointed director of the Gary, Indiana Neighborhood House. It was while working in Gary that he met and married Maurine Fink, his companion for the next 58 years.
In 1930, the couple was called to New York by the Presbyterian Board of National Missions to work for the office of City, Immigrant, and Industrial Work. From New York they were called to direct the Dodge Neighborhood House in Detroit, Michigan. They arrived in the midst of the depression and the struggle to organize the United Automobile Workers. It was during their stay in Detroit that their two children David and Sandra were born.
After thirteen years in Detroit, the Presbyterian Board of Foreign Missions invited the Jones family to China in 1947. Working with the Church of Christ in China Henry became a pioneer in the field of industrial mission. As the communists rose to power Jones sent his wife and two children home in 1948. He remained in China until 1950.
Back in the United States, Reverend Jones served pastorates in the Dubuque, Iowa Presbytery between 1950 and 1953. In late 1953, Jones was recalled to the mission field. Originally assigned to India, visa complications caused him to go to Japan instead. It was during this time in Japan that the first Asian Conference on Industrial Evangelism was held in Manila. The conference included representatives from sixteen Asian countries.
Jones's first stint in Japan ended in 1957. While awaiting recall he served as a worldwide traveling consultant before returning to Japan in 1962. After three years the Joneses retired from foreign mission. During his "retirement" Jones served as interim pastor in nine different Michigan churches. In 1985 he made his retirement official at the age of 85.
In their later years, the Joneses maintained contact with many Asian acquaintances, even returning to China to visit in 1979. They were also instrumental in bringing several students from Asia to study in the United States. In 1981 Henry Jones was honored with the G.R.A.C.E. (Grand Rapids Area Center For Ecumenism) award. McCormick Seminary similarly honored him in 1985, for his lifetime commitment to mission.
In addition to his years of devoted service to his Church, the Rev. Jones was also interested in the experiences of the Welsh in America. He was particularly concerned with the history of Welsh churches and religious song festivals in Michigan.
The papers of Rev. Henry D. Jones consist of one linear foot of materials from 1918 to 1987. The collection is arranged topically and chronologically. Each folder is also chronologically arranged. The collection is divided into seven series, including: Pastoral Career and Home Mission, Foreign Mission Activity, Later Career, Correspondence, Articles and Biography, Photographs, and Welsh in Michigan.
China -- History -- Republic, 1912-1949.; Clergy -- Japan.; Clergy -- China.; Japan.; Missionaries -- China.; Missionaries -- Japan.; Welsh-Americans -- Michigan.; China -- Missions.; Japan -- Missions.; Missionaries -- Japan.; Missionaries -- China.; Missions -- China.; Missions -- Japan.; Diaries.; Photographs.; Jones, Henry D. (Henry David), 1900-1987.; Presbyterian Church -- Missions -- Japan.; Presbyterian Church -- Missions -- China.; Presbyterian Church.; Ripon College.; Jones, Henry D. (Henry David), 1900-1987.; Presbyterian Church -- Missions -- Japan.; Presbyterian Church -- Missions -- China.
- Pastoral Career and Home Mission
  Pastoral Career and Home Mission consists of 1.5 inches of material covering 1918-1947 and 1950-1953. The first span of dates includes a diary kept at Ripon College, papers written while in McCormick Seminary, as well as material about each of the three neighborhood houses he directed. Also included is a survey made in 1930 of Hamilton, Ohio. The second span concerns his pastorate after his evacuation from China and prior to his departure for Japan. This includes two wills, a travel account and church contracts.
  - Diary detailing study at Ripon College and service in SATC, September 23, 1918-November 17, 1918 (Box 1)
  - Sermon Outlines and papers from McCormick Theological Seminary, circa 1924 (Box 1)
  - Howell House (Chicago, Il.), 1955 (Box 1)
    (excerpt from program on Henry Jones's work as staff member, 1923-1925)
  - Anniversary booklet from Gary Neighborhood House (Gary, Ind.) and newspaper article about its closing, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Church Survey of Hamilton, Ohio made by Henry D. Jones for the Board of National Missions., October 10, 1930-November 7, 1930 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters 1945 and correspondence, 1953 concerning Dodge Community House in Detroit, 1945-1953 (Box 1)
  - Sermons given by Henry D. Jones, circa 1950 (Box 1)
  - Calls to pastorate in Iowa and Missouri, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Last will and testament of Henry and Maurine Jones 1950, 1953 and listing of properties owned in, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Handbill advertising closing out sale at manse in Wadena, Iowa prior to departing for mission in, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Board of Foreign Missions Travel Account, 1953 (Box 1)
- Foreign Missionary Activities
  Foreign Missionary Activity consists of 1.5 inches of material from 1947 to 1964. This material concerns mission work in China and Japan. It includes reports, bulletins and letters regarding the communist rise to power as well as Chinese pamphlets on occupational evangelism. One folder concerns the organizing of the East Asian Christian Conferences.
  - Membership Certificate and Annual Reports of the Community Church of Shanghai, 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets written in Chinese on Occupational Evangelism (Box 1)
    (with one English translation)
  - International Labor Day letter and brochure-National Christian Council of China, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Reports and letters to the Presbyterian Board of Foreign Missions, 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - "Confidential" Bulletins on Communist occupation of China from Foreign Mission and Overseas Church Service to families of missionaries remaining in China, 1948-1950 (Box 1)
  - Church of Christ in China English News Bulletin, December 1950 (Box 1)
  - Certificate of Appointment to Overseas Mission cards, 1953; 1959 (Box 1)
  - East Asian Christian Conference organizational letters and reports, 1956-1959; 1962-1964 (Box 1)
- Later Career (Retirement)
  Later Career consists of 1.5 inches of material from 1975 to 1987, during retirement. Included within this series are tributes and awards as well as material from Westminster Presbyterian Church in Grand Rapids, Michigan.
  - Contract 1975 Commendation, 1980 and Retirement from Westminster Presbyterian Church, Grand Rapids, Michigan, 1985, 1975-1985 (Box 1)
  - China Trip, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Church Labor Letter No. 142, May 1980 (Box 1)
    (contains Tribute to Henry D. Jones)
  - Grand Rapids Area Center for Ecumenism (G.R.A.C.E.) Award and articles about award, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Citation from McCormick Theological Seminary and commencement program, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Anniversary Information for World Council of Churches-Urban Rural Mission, 1987 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  Correspondence includes 4 inches of correspondence mainly from 1947 to 1958, but also including one letter from 1935 and a correspondence carried out between 1979-1987 largely concerning bringing an Asian student to America to study. Also contained in this series are yearly Christmas letters from 1948 to 1987. Often these are form letters, but they contain a great deal of information. Other correspondence includes letters from their two children written from 1947 to 1958.
  - May 1, 1935 (Box 1)
  - 1947 (Box 1)
    (First trip to China)
  - 1948 (Box 1)
  - 1949 (Box 1)
  - 1950 (Box 1)
  - November 1, 1950-December 20, 1950 (Box 1)
    (From Latin America Trip)
  - 1952-1953 (Box 1)
  - 1954 (Box 1)
  - 1955 (Box 1)
  - 1956 (Box 1)
  - 1957 (Box 1)
  - 1958 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Children, Sandra and David, 1947-1958 (Box 1)
  - Irving Y.Y. Ling and others largely concerning Fang Ling's admission to Grand Valley College, 1958; 1979-1986 (Box 1)
  - Christmas letters, 1948-1986 (Box 1)
- Articles and Biography
  Articles and Biography has, as the name implies, biographical information as well as material for articles and various articles by Henry D. Jones. Several newspaper clippings are housed with the biographical information.
  - Articles and material for articles on urban situation in S.E. Asia, circa 1950-1960 (Box 1)
  - Articles and material, circa 1950-1960 (Box 1)
  - Biographies and newspaper clippings, 1928-1987 (Box 1)
    (includes "Through My Eyes")
- Photographs
  Photographs, the final series, is made up of individual and group pictures mainly concerning foreign mission work. Three photograph albums are included containing material on foreign mission work in China and Japan.
  - Photographs
    - Individual and Family (Box 1)
    - Group (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Photograph Albums
    - "Shanghai Friends,", 1950 (Box 1)
    - Japan, 1953-1957 (Box 1)
    - Occupational Evangelism Caravan, 1956 (Box 1)
- Welsh in Michigan
  Welsh in Michigan includes 1 inch of correspondence, 1969 to 1986 (bulk dates 1981-1985), between the Reverend Jones and individuals interested in documenting the Welsh in Michigan. A second file of 1.5 inches of materials, 1968 to 1975 (bulk dates 1968-1971 and 1982-1985), includes information and programs of Welsh song festivals and histories of the Welsh United Presbyterian Church of Detroit and the Orchard Lake Community Presbyterian Church.
  - Correspondence, Henry D. Jones, 1969-1986 (Box 1)
  - Song Festivals and Church Histories, 1968-1985 (Box 1)